-=蓝光电影网=-
blu-raydisc.tv
下载更多蓝光高清电影-3D电影
请到-=蓝光电影网=-
NARRATOR: Only time can teach us
what is truth and what is legend.
Some truths do not survive the ages.
But the legend of the child
with the blue eyes will live forever...
...and be whispered in all four winds
of the Great White Mountains.
We, the Yagahl, were hunters
of the mightiest of all beasts...
...the Mannak.
But our world began to change.
The Mannaks came later and later
to our valley...
...and there were times
when they did not come at all.
Our hunters grew restless.
And our people grew hungry.
Only one amongst us...
...the one we call "Old Mother,"
the last of her kind...
...only she could speak
to the spirits of the earth...
...and ask the wisdom of the Fathers
to save our people.
Many times she asks...
...until one night they answered her call
and sent us a sign.
A sign of the beginning of the end.
HUNTER: We found her in the mountains.
She was holding on to a dead woman.
The Fathers have sent her.
She came to tell us
of four-legged demons...
...that will put an end to our world.
They will come to our valley
at the time when...
...we go on our last hunt.
But do not fear.
From this hunt a warrior will arise...
...and this one will be his woman.
They will lead us into a new life...
...where the Yagahl
will know hunger no more.
That night...
...Old Mother did not see the face
of the warrior of which she spoke...
...but she knew that the child
with the blue eyes...
...was a blessing she must protect.
To our people, she was Evolet...
...the promise of life.
To a boy named D'Leh,
she was much more than that.
Only one of the Yagahl did not believe in
Old Mother's prophecy:
The young boy's father...
...the one who carried the White Spear
and blew the whistle for the hunt.
I will watch over your son
as if he were my own.
I know you will. But promise me
you will tell no one why I left.
We cannot wait for the last hunt.
- Good throw! Throw again!
- Good throw!
Ka'ren?
Ka'ren? Hmm?
No. Not you.
Your father abandoned our people.
Go away.
Fight well!
You must win, Ka'ren!
TIC'TIC:
Leave him!
Ka'ren! I said leave him!
D'Leh.
He is the son of a coward.
You never say that again.
Any of you.
BO Y:
Good throw.
You are alone...
...like me.
What happened to your people?
They were killed...
...by four-legged demons.
You will never be alone, Evolet.
Do you see that light?
That one?
It does not move across the sky
like all the others do.
That light is like you in my heart.
It will never go away.
It will never go away?
No, never.
OLD MOTHER:
Evolet, come here.
Don't stray from the hut
without telling me.
And for many moons...
...Evolet and D'Leh
looked at each other...
...and the love in their hearts
grew stronger.
Until finally, after many years...
...the day of the last hunt arrived.
BAKU: D'Leh, how long do we
have to keep watch?
Until the Mannaks come.
And when will they come?
Do not know.
D'Leh, when will I become a hunter?
When you stop asking
so many questions.
The Great Hunter Tic'Tic
came to Old Mother's hut today.
She thinks the time of prophecy
has come.
She told him not to kill
the Mannak this hunt.
She thinks Ka'ren will win the White Spear
and claim Evolet.
- Baku, look what I found for you.
- Ah.
Mm.
You know what a good hunter Ka'ren is.
We must run away. Together,
we can cross the Great Mountains.
And abandon our people? Like my father?
I cannot do that.
I worked on this for many moons.
The only way we can be together
is I must kill the Mannak.
They are here! They are here! Look!
Look how many there are.
Today...
...I will not pierce the heart of the Mannak.
It will be one of you.
One of you will claim the White Spear.
May the Fathers of the Yagahl...
...and the spirit of the mighty Mannak
choose the best of you.
MOHA:
Ka'ren, you have the first throw.
LU'KIBU: Ka'ren, the Mannak is yours.
You will be our leader.
D'Leh? What about you?
I hunt to win Evolet.
We hunt together as one!
HUNTER:
Tic'Tic found the lead bull.
TIC'TIC:
Slow down!
D'Leh!
They're breaking away! Bring them back!
Baku! They're coming!
They're coming, Baku!
They're coming! They're coming!
The last one is coming! It is a big bull!
HUNTER:
Now!
MOHA: D'Leh is coming!
Ka'ren, make your throw!
Keep him down! Hold the net!
He is too strong! Let go, Ka'ren!
D'Leh, we have to let go!
I can't! My hand is caught!
LU'KIBU:
Look! Look!
It's D'Leh!
BAKU:
You killed him! All alone!
No one has ever done that.
That was brave.
D'Leh killed the Mannak!
He did not let go of the net!
He was the only one!
What are you waiting for?
Wise Spirit, I killed the Mannak.
I claim the White Spear...
...and with it my woman...
...Evolet.
From that day on, D'Leh was no longer
the son of a coward.
Now the Yagahl would honor his name...
...for bringing to them the blessings
of the Mannak for one last time.
And though Old Mother was pleased
in her heart to see Evolet so happy...
...she feared in her soul...
...that the one who had slayed
the mighty beast...
...did not have the courage
for what was to come.
Why does Tic'Tic not celebrate with us?
- D'Leh?
- There is something I must do.
What do you want?
I was not brave.
And I did not hunt as one.
The Fathers of the Yagahl
played with us today.
What should I do?
If I give up the White Spear,
I give up Evolet. I cannot do that.
Is she yours to give up?
Hmm?
It is not the way of the Yagahl
to claim the White Spear with a lie.
I gave the White Spear back to Tic'Tic.
Why would you do such a thing?
Because I did not kill the Mannak, Evolet.
- Of course you did, you held on to the net.
- No, I lied.
I tried to let go like all the others.
My hand was caught in it.
After that, the Mannak ran into my spear.
I did nothing.
Evolet, remember what I told you
about our light?
I still feel the same.
You will always be in my heart.
That will never go away.
But still...
...you gave me up.
That night the great white rain
came to the valley of the Yagahl.
And like an icy veil,
sadness fell over D'Leh's heart.
And with the white rain
came the four-legged demons.
OLD MOTHER:
You stay here.
Baku.
Moha! Look out!
[SPEAKING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
- Baku, hide.
- Yes, Mother.
TIC'TIC:
D'Leh!
We cannot help them!
[SPEAKS IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
Please.
Let me!
Let me go!
- What are you doing?
- I am going after them.
Over the Great Mountains?
That is not possible.
D'LEH:
They came over the Great Mountains.
They are demons. Maybe they can fly.
I did not see wings on them.
You think you can bring them down
all alone? Only you?
TIC'TIC:
He is not alone.
I go with him.
Without the other hunters,
we all will die.
I will go too.
No, Baku, you will stay here.
But you, Ka'ren, you must go with them.
Don't touch me!
[SPEAKS IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
And as they bid farewell to the elders
and the children of our people...
...the Wise Spirit of the Yagahl blessed them
and the spears by their side.
Old Mother knew they would
never be hunters again...
...but warriors instead.
It will be night soon. We stay here.
No, we go on. We are getting closer.
I cannot see in the dark. Can you?
We stay here. We eat and sleep.
Why do you not carry the White Spear?
Are you afraid?
Answer.
Ka'ren, go to sleep.
Baku? Baku!
What are you doing here? Go home.
I can help you. I can carry a water bag.
Go home!
They killed my mother!
He's alone.
He will only slow us down.
D'Leh, I'm thirsty.
Fire still lives in these stones.
D'Leh!
She's alive. We must hurry.
Why is Old Mother freeZing?
The white rain is not a friend
to the hunter.
It swallowed all the marks
of the stolen brothers and sisters.
It was now up to the Fathers of the Yagahl
to guide their way.
And they walked for many days and nights
to a faraway land...
...where the Great Mountains ended...
...and where the story of
the child with the blue eyes began.
The place where the four-legged demons
killed Evolet's people.
We've walked for days now,
and still no marks.
Maybe they do have wings.
TIC'TIC:
Maybe they do.
But our brothers and sisters do not.
Don't forget to chew.
[SPEAKING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
Maybe she only lost it.
It is hot here.
Baku. Stay close.
[SPEAKING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
What was that?
We must free them tonight.
Not tonight. This is not a good place.
They know there is danger,
and they keep a good watch.
We'll do the same.
I will go first, then Ka'ren, then you.
D'Leh.
Come.
I understand your pain.
But you must be patient.
D'Leh.
I will never give you up again.
This way.
Come.
[SPEAKING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
D'Leh!
Run! Run!
MAN:
D'Leh!
D'LEH:
This way!
Over here! This way!
Go! Go!
D'LEH:
Ka'ren!
TIC'TIC:
Run!
D'LEH: Tic'Tic!
- Go!
Tic'Tic!
D'Leh! Evolet! Up here!
- D'Leh!
- I will lead them away.
- No, do not go!
- I will come back for you.
I promise.
Oh, Baku.
You should not be here.
[SPEAKING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
I think he speaks of D'Leh.
再试一次
我会把你们杀掉
永远不要
永远别想再从我身逃跑
D'Leh will come back.
He promised it to me.
Ka'ren. Do you think he's still alive?
It does not matter now.
He tried to save us.
Forgive me, Tic'Tic.
I should have listened to you.
Do not die.
I will bring you food.
Old Mother was watching over their journey
with all her strength...
...and her spirit stayed always
by their side.
But that night, she could not rule over
the forces of the earth...
...and could not stop the waters
of the heavens.
D'Leh would have to face alone...
...the mighty beast
who rules these lands.
Ha! Ha!
Do not eat me when I set you free!
I feared you were dead.
Do not fear for me.
Look, over there.
There was an attack.
I heard them scream.
This is where they went.
[YELLING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
Tic'Tic, move away. Go.
D'Leh, come back.
Move away.
You must remember me.
I gave you life.
You speak to the Spear Tooth?
How do you come to speak our words?
[SPEAKING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
You not like Naku food?
It's different, but good.
[SPEAKING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
We come from over the mountains.
- We know where you come from.
D'LEH: How do you know?
And how do you come
to speak our words?
A man come from the mountain before.
He was looking for new land.
Our wise man told me to learn his words.
You. You have his face.
What happened to him?
He was taken a long time ago.
Taken where?
Come.
NAKUDU: When your father came to us,
he became my friend.
Then the evil spirits stole your father,
like many of our people.
They bring them to the nest
of the great birds...
...and fly away over the sand.
TIC'TIC:
Where do they take them?
To the mountain of the gods.
No one has ever returned.
[MAN SPEAKING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
NAKUDU:
Our wise man says you will lead us there.
Me?
We have a telling that...
...one day the one will come...
...who will free our people.
The one who speaks to the Spear Tooth.
NARRATOR: At last, the brave people
of the Naku buried their dead.
They sent word to all the tribes
of the land...
...that the one who speaks
to the Spear Tooth had come.
Their call...
...was a call for war.
Why do they think
I can free their people?
There's something you must know
about your father.
When your mother died
bringing you life...
...your father took upon himself
not only the weight of you...
...but all our people.
We were starving.
He could not wait for Old Mother's
prophecy to come true.
Your father did not run away.
He left to save our people.
How could you let me believe all this time
that my father betrayed us?
Because he wanted it to be that way.
Your father carried the White Spear.
He feared that when he left, others would
follow him and abandon our people.
And why do you tell me this now?
A good man...
...draws a circle around himself
and cares for those within.
His woman, his children.
Other men draw a larger circle...
...and bring within
their brothers and sisters.
But some men...
...have a great destiny.
They must draw around themselves...
...a circle that includes
many, many more.
Your father was one of those men.
You must decide for yourself...
...whether you are, as well.
This is Kawu, our fastest runner.
[SPEAKING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
He bring words from the people
who live that way.
They stole many more men.
And now they are moving
to the great birds, fast.
We must find them
before they reach these birds.
[SPEAKS IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
You have no woman?
The day before you came...
...they took her breath...
...and they stole our son.
[SPEAKS IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
[YELLING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
I am Baku.
Tudu.
No. I am Baku.
Baku, Tudu. Baku, Tudu.
[SPEAKS IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
He's killing him! You must help!
[SPEAKING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
The word of the Naku traveled fast
and from all winds came many warriors.
The Tutt Tutt who move like big running
birds and hide their eyes behind trees.
The tribe of the Kula.
They are short like our young ones.
And from the valley without sun
came the ones with blood on their heads.
But the strongest of them all
were the Hoda.
Their leader spoke for all the warriors
of the land.
Tell him if his people walk with us,
we will bring them down.
[SPEAKING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
He says you are only a boy.
Tell him I am older than I look.
Quina is Hoda. Hoda do not laugh.
Hmm.
- Yahalah!
ALL: Yahalah!
They walked faster and faster
and did not slow down to eat or to rest.
And more spears joined them
with each passing day.
[SPEAKING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
This word "Yahalah," what does it mean?
They are your words.
"We must bring them down."
[SPEAKING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
The great birds have arrived.
Evolet!
Baku, D'Leh is here.
BAKU:
D'Leh!
Tudu! Tudu!
Tudu!
Tudu, that man with the spear,
he will not give up.
Him with her.
- Ew.
- Maybe the boy is right.
D'Leh cannot fly over water
like they can.
Who would've thought
he could find so many spears?
[SPEAKING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
NAKUDU:
This river moves like a snake in the sand.
He says the eye of the snake
rests under the sun...
...and under the moon it does not move.
Is there a shorter way
to the head of the snake?
We must look beyond the great sand.
But no one can walk that far.
The mountains and the sand...
...they all look the same,
and we will lose our way.
We will all die.
We will find the head of the snake.
And we will free our people.
We must rest.
The man from the river
had spoken the truth.
They had walked in circles for many days
and lost their way.
And the eye of the snake
was nowhere to be found.
[SPEAKING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
Tic'Tic, Tic'Tic.
I have found the eye of the snake.
You see that light?
That one? Remember
what the river people said?
It rests under the sun,
but under the moon it does not move.
Nakudu, tell them what I said.
It will guide us to the head of the snake.
And as the last moon had come
to the valley of the Yagahl...
...it seemed that all spirits
had left Old Mother.
She did not eat or speak
for many moons...
...because she knew
there was one last destiny to fulfill.
Wise Spirit...
...it's me, Katan.
NAKUDU:
The mountains of the gods.
And the head of the snake.
Evolet. You are well.
Shh. Do not speak.
[SPEAKING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
KA'REN:
Baku, over here.
How can men do such a thing
to Father Mannak?
They are not men like us, Baku.
Then what are they?
Some say they came from the stars.
Others believe that they flew across
the great water...
...when their land sank into the sea.
[SPEAKING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
No! Moha!
Moha!
There are too many of them
for every one of us.
No one can bring them down.
No, D'Leh.
The ones they force to do their work...
...they are even more.
Do you think they will fight with us?
That is for you to find out.
Hmm?
[SPEAKING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
Ah, D'Leh.
D'Leh.
NAKUDU: Tudu.
D'LEH: Do not be afraid, Baku.
I'll bring you home.
Where is Evolet?
The women sleep in different huts,
but I saw her today.
Tic'Tic is waiting with many spears,
behind the sand.
They killed Moha today.
He was sacrificed.
It was my mistake that put you
in this terrible place.
I need your forgiveness.
The Fathers chose you to lead us...
...and we will stand by your side.
[SPEAKING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
Tell him how many spears we have.
Ask him to fight with us.
He says the number of spear
does not matter.
- Men cannot bring down gods.
- Shh.
[SPEAKING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
He says the blind man
knows much about the gods.
He was once their servant but ran away.
They have hidden him here ever since.
Wise man...
...tell us more of these gods.
[SPEAKING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
NAKUDU: First, there were three,
but now there's only one left.
There must be a way to defeat him.
He said, once...
...only once, he heard the god
speak of one he fears.
They have a telling of one
who wears a mark...
...that you can see in the sky at night.
They call it Uru-Anna,
the Mark of the Hunter.
The brightest star of all heaven.
He asks if you wear
the Mark of the Hunter.
Without the mark,
you cannot bring down the god.
D'LEH:
Wait, wait. The band on your arm...
...where did you get it?
NAKUDU:
From the man who saved his life.
Where is he?
His bones are buried in the sand
with all the others.
He wants to know why
you ask of this man.
He was my father.
[SPEAKS IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
D'LEH:
Ask him where Tic'Tic is.
They found us!
I am full with days.
Please, great hunter, do not say that.
We need you.
They will not fight with us.
They have their own prophecy.
D'Leh...
...a prophecy has many faces,
many ways to come true.
Your father...
Your father, he gave this to me.
- No, great hunter, this is yours.
- Take it.
Be as your father.
[SPEAKS IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
[SPEAKING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
把它给我
把刀给我们
快看她手上的伤痕！
它们的形状像.......
那个记号
我们找到那个记号了
在一个奴隶的手上
[SPEAKS IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
[SPEAKING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
NAKUDU:
D'Leh...
...I know how it feels
to lose a good friend.
Your father was mine.
I barely remember him.
He remembered you.
His heart hurt when he spoke of
a young boy behind the Great Mountains.
He was preparing to leave
to go back to you.
That is when he was taken.
D'Leh...
...the men are waiting.
We, the people of the Yagahl...
[NAKUDU SPEAKING
IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
...hunt the mightiest of beasts,
the Mannak.
He is great and we are small,
and still we bring him down.
Because we hunt together, as one.
When the sun rises...
...we will join our brothers and sisters
on the mountain of the god...
...and convince them to fight with us,
together, as one!
What is happening?
Listen, Baku,
today you must become a hunter.
Me?
[SPEAKS IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
D'LEH:
Yahalah.
[SPEAKING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
Look, Ka'ren, look.
- That one.
- Him?
Baku, we found the lead bull. Go!
Now!
Quina, not yet!
Ha! Ha!
- They will not charge.
- The Mannak have been beaten too long.
Ka'ren, look.
You must move everybody up the ramp!
- Move! Move!
- Go! Go!
Ka'ren! No!
Yahalah!
- Yahalah!
ALL: Yahalah!
[SPEAKING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
Yahalah!
Stop!
He says the one who follow this woman
should turn back or she will die.
Like this traitor.
Turn back to your mountains
and you can take your woman.
Tell him I will take his offer.
Tell him I accept.
Tell him!
But I will take all my people with me.
Each and every Yagahl.
Tell him!
They are yours!
Ask him what will happen to the others.
They belong to the god, he says.
They will do his work, forever.
No.
They will not.
He is not a god!
EVOLET:
D'Leh!
Evolet!
Baku!
Tudu!
No!
KATAN:
Help! Help! She's bleeding!
[SPEAKS IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
You came for me.
No, no, please.
Please.
To have journeyed so far...
...to have walked to the end
of the world...
...to bring down the one
they called the Almighty...
...only to return without Evolet.
This was not what Old Mother
had foretold.
But just as she was lost to him forever...
...the legend of the child
with the blue eyes began.
NAKUDU:
Evolet and D'Leh!
Evolet had brought the promise of life
to our people.
And now, with her last breath...
...Old Mother had given it back.
NAKUDU: Your father wanted to
bring these back to you.
They will feed your people.
Tell them the people of the Yagahl
thank the Naku people.
Thank you, brother Nakudu.
My heart walks with you, brother D'Leh.
That was the last time
they saw their friends the Naku.
And then the long journey home began.
BO Y:
They're back! They're back!
And as the ones who walked
with the Fathers...
...looked down on them
and guided their way...
...so the Yagahl looked to Evolet and D'Leh
to guide their people.
And when the first moon was born again
to their valley...
...it brought with it
the first fruits of their land.
Look how fast it is growing.
And so it came to pass
that the promise of life...
...was fulfilled.
只有时间才能告诉我们什么是真相
什么是传说
有些真相流传不了几个时代
但是那个有着蓝色眼睛的孩子的传说
却会永远流传下去
在“圣冷山”的四面八方被低声诉说着
我们雅格哈人
狩猎最强大的兽中之王
“曼纳克”
但是我们的世界开始有了变化
“曼纳克”到我们村子的时间越来越晚
甚至有时候他们根本不出现
我们的猎者愈发焦虑
我们的族人愈发饥饿
只有一个人
我们称她作“圣婆”
她是她们这种人的最后一个
只有她能对大地之灵说话
向“父”的智慧询求解救族人的方法
[CHANTING]
她问了一次又一次
直到有一天晚上他们回答了她
并送来一个预兆
[GIRL WHIMPERING]
预兆着一切的结束即将开始
我们在山里发现的她
她在一个死去的妇女身边
[CHANTING]
是“父”把她送来的
[PANTING]
她来告诉我们有“四脚魔”
会最终毁灭我们的世界
他们会在我们最后一次狩猎的时候
来到我们的村子
但是不要畏惧
在这次狩猎中将诞生一位战士
并且她将成为他的女人
他们会带领我们步入新的生活
到时候我们雅格哈人将永远不再有饥饿
那一夜
“圣婆”没有看到她所谓的战士的脸
但是她知道
那个蓝色眼睛的女孩
是一种祝福，她必须加以保护
对我们的人来说，艾弗拉特
是我们生命的希望
但对一个叫迪雷的男孩
她的意义远不止如此
只有一个雅格哈人不相信“圣婆”的预言
那个小男孩的父亲
他掌管着“白矛”
并负责吹哨发起狩猎的信号
我会好好照看你的儿子
将他视若己出
我知道你会的，但是请答应我
不要告诉任何人我离开的原因
我们不能等到最后一次的狩猎
[GRUNTS]
- 投的好！再来一次！
- 投的好！
凯伦？
凯伦？嗯？
不，不要跟你
你父亲抛弃了我们的族人
滚
打啊！
你一定要赢，凯伦！
放开他！
凯伦！我让你放开他！
迪雷
他是懦夫的儿子
永远不许再这样说
任何人都不许
投的好！
你是一个人
跟我一样
你的族人都怎么了？
他们都被杀了
被“四脚魔”
你以后不再是一个人了，艾佛拉特
你看到那颗星了么？
那一颗？
它不会像其他星星一样走过天空
你在我心里就像那颗星一样
它永远不会离开
它永远不会离开么？
是的，永远
艾弗拉特，过来
不要不告诉我就离开屋子
很多个夜晚
艾弗拉特和迪雷看着彼此
他们的爱越来越深
片名：《史前一万年》
直到很多年以后，终于
最后一次狩猎的日子到来了
迪雷，我们我这样看多久啊？
直到“曼纳克”出现
那他们什么时候出现呢？
不知道
迪雷，我什么时候能成为猎者啊？
等到你不再问这么多问题的时候
今天伟大的猎者提提去了“圣婆”的屋子
她认为预言里的时刻已经到来了
她叫他这次狩猎中不要去杀“曼纳克”
她认为凯伦会赢得“白矛”和艾弗拉特
[FOOTSTEPS APPRO ACHING]
- 巴库，看我给我给你带什么来了
- 啊
嗯
你知道凯伦是个多厉害的猎者
我们必须要逃走
我们可以一直跨过“圣山”
然后抛弃我们的族人？
像我父亲一样？
我不能这样做
这个我做了很多天
唯一能使我们在一起的方法
是我必须杀死“曼纳克”
[MANNAKS TRUMPETING]
他们来了！他们来了！看！
看看他们有多少
[CHATTERING]
今天
刺穿“曼纳克”心脏的将不是我
而是你们其中的一个
“白矛”将属于你们之中的一个
希望雅格哈的“父”
和强大的“曼纳克”之灵
挑选出你们之中最优秀的一个
[YELLING]
凯伦，你第一个投
凯伦，“曼纳克”是你的了
你将成为我们的领袖
迪雷，你呢？
我为了艾弗拉特而猎
我们要齐心协力
提提找到领头牛了
[YELLING]
[GROWLING]
[RO ARING]
[MANNAKS TRUMPETING]
[WHISTLE BLOWS]
[YELLING]
慢！
迪雷！
他们散开了！把他们赶回来！
[SHOUTING]
[GRUNTS]
巴库！他们来了！
他们来了！巴库！
他们来了！他们来了！
最后一只到了！那是只大牛！
动手！
[TRUMPETING]
迪雷来了！
凯伦，快投啊！
稳住它！抓住网！
[SHOUTING]
[GRUNTING]
他力气太大了！放手，凯伦！
迪雷，我们得放手！
不行！我的手卡住了！
[RO ARS]
看！看啊！
是迪雷！
[GASPING]
你杀了他！一个人！
从来没有人这样
太勇敢了
[CHEERING]
迪雷杀了“曼纳克”！
他没有松开网！
他是唯一一个！
你还等什么呢？
智慧之灵，我杀了“曼纳克”
我将拥有“白矛”
和我的女人
艾弗拉特
[CHEERING]
从那一天开始，
迪雷不再是懦夫的儿子
整个雅格哈都以他为荣
他带给他们来自最后一次的“曼纳克”
带来的祝福
虽然“圣婆”看到艾弗拉特如此快乐
心里也十分高兴
但是她的灵魂却在害怕
怕这个杀死猛兽的人
没有勇气面对即将到来的一切
[CHANTING]
为什么提提不跟我们一起庆祝呢？
- 迪雷？
- 我有点事情必须要做
你想干嘛？
我并不勇敢
我也没有独自杀死猛兽
雅格哈的“父”今天愚弄了我们
我该怎么办呢？
我放弃“白矛”就等于放弃艾弗拉特
我不能这么做
她由得你去放弃么？
嗯？
雅格哈的人不能用谎言赢得“白矛”
我把“白矛”还给提提了
为什么要这样做？
因为我没有杀死“曼纳克”，艾弗拉特
- 当然是你杀的，你抓住那个网没有松手
- 不是的，我撒了谎
我像其他人一样想要松手
但是我的手卡住了
之后，“曼纳克”跑向我的矛
我什么都没做
艾弗拉特，记得我跟你说过
我们的那颗星么？
我还是一样的
你永远在我心里
永远不会离开
可是
你还是放弃了我
那天晚上一场大雪降临雅格哈的村庄
悲伤像一层冰纱
笼罩在迪雷的心里
随着这场大雪
“四脚魔”出现了
[SNORING]
[GASPS]
你留在这儿
巴库
[SHOUTING]
莫哈！小心！
[GRUNTING]
不要杀死他们
都抓起来
- 巴库，藏起来
- 是的，妈妈
迪雷！
我们阻止不了他们！
把她绑在我的马后面
求求你！
放了我！
放了我吧！
- 你干什么呢？
- 我要跟着他们
跨过“圣山”？那是不可能的！
他们从“圣山”的另一边来的
他们是魔鬼，说不定他们会飞
我没看到他们长翅膀，你呢？
你觉得你能阻止他们么？
凭你一个人？
他不是一个人
我跟他一起
如果没了其他的猎者
我们最后都会死
我也去
不行，巴库，你留在这里
但是你，凯伦，你必须一起去
[CHATTERING]
别碰我！
[MEN LAUGHING]
（外来语）
当他们跟村子里的老人跟孩子告别的时候
雅格哈的智慧之灵祝福他们
和他们身旁的矛
“圣婆”知道他们再也不是猎者了
他们是战士
天快黑了，我们在这里休息
不，我们继续走吧，已经很近了
我在黑夜里看不见，你呢？
我们就在这里，吃东西睡觉
为什么你不要“白矛”？
你怕了么？
回答我
凯伦，睡觉了
巴库？巴库！
你在这儿干嘛？快回家！
我能帮上忙！我可以拿水壶！
回去！
他们杀了我妈妈！
他只剩一个人
他只会拖慢我们
迪雷，我好渴
石头里的火还没灭
迪雷！
她还活着！我们得快
[WIND HOWLING]
[PANTING]
为什么“圣婆”冷得发抖？
这场大雪显然不想帮助猎者
它吞噬了被掠走的兄弟姐妹的足迹
现在只能靠雅格哈的“父”
指引他们的道路
他们向一个遥远的地方
走了许多个日夜
“圣山”在那里结束
而那个蓝眼睛孩子的传说
就在那里开始
“四脚魔”在这里
杀死了艾弗拉特的族人
我们已经走了很多天了
还是没有足迹
说不定他们真的有翅膀
也许他们的确有
但是我们的兄弟姐妹没有
别忘了嚼
[MEN SHOUTING]
这婊子留下了记号
我喜欢你的精神
但我要摧毁它
[GRUNTING]
也许她只是掉了
[BIRDS SHRIEKING]
这里好热
巴库，跟紧了
[ANIMAL GROWLING]
[WHIP CRACKS]
[YELLS]
[RO ARING]
[MEN SHOUTING INDISTINCTLY]
[MAN SCREAMING]
[RO ARING]
[HORSE WHINNYING]
（外来语）
那是什么啊?
[SHOUTING INDISTINCTLY]
我们今晚必须救他们出来
今晚不行，这不是个好地方
他们知道这里有危险
所以处处小心
我们也要这样
我先守夜，然后凯伦，然后是你
迪雷
过来
我明白你的痛处
但是你得耐心
[ANIMAL GROWLS]
[HORSE WHINNYING]
你的魔咒
也许对我的主人有效
但是对我
没有用
迪雷
我永远不会再放弃你了
[ANIMAL GROWLS]
这边
来
（外来语）
[GRUNTING]
迪雷！
跑！快跑！
这边！
[GRUNTS]
这边！走这边！
跑！跑！
凯伦！
[ANIMAL GROWLS]
[GROWLING]
[HORSE WHINNIES]
[SCREECHING]
[MAN SCREAMING]
快跑！
跑！
- 提提！
- 走！
提提！
[YELLING]
[GRUNTING]
[RO ARING]
迪雷！艾弗拉特！上来！
- 迪雷！
- 我去把他们引开
- 不要，别走！
- 我会回来找你的
我保证
[GRUNTS]
[SHOUTING]
[RO ARS]
哦，巴库
你不应该来的
[HORSE WHINNIES]
他是谁？
他可能在说迪雷
迪雷会回来的
他向我保证过
[WHEEZING]
凯伦，你觉得他还活着么？
已经无所谓了
他试着救我们
[GRUNTING]
[PANTING]
[HORSE WHINNIES]
[MEN SHOUTING INDISTINCTLY]
[GRUNTING]
原谅我，提提
我应该听你的
不要死
我会给你找吃的来
[YELLING]
[FLIES BUZZING]
[RO ARS]
[GASPING]
“圣婆”用她的全部力量
注视着他们的旅程
她的灵一直守他们的身旁
[THUNDER CRASHING]
但是那天晚上
她控制不了来自大地的力量
也阻止不了来自天堂的水流下
迪雷要自己面对
那只统治这片土地的神兽
[COUGHING]
[GROWLING]
哈！哈！
[GRUNTS]
如果我放了你，不许吃我！
[GROWLING]
[SNIFFING]
[ROCKS CLATTERING]
我怕你已经死了
别为我担心
看，在那边
他们受到了一场攻击
我听到他们惨嚎
这是他们去的地方
（外来语）
[RO ARING]
提提，移开，走
迪雷，回来
走开
你一定还记得我
我救了你的命
[GROWLING]
你可以跟“利齿”说话？
你怎么会讲我们的语言？
（外来语）
[PANTING]
你不喜欢纳库的食物？
[HICCUPS]
有点特别，不过很好
（外来语）
[CHEERING]
我们来自山的另一边
- 我们知道你们从哪儿来的
- 你们怎么知道的？
还有你怎么会我们的语言？
以前也有个人从山的另一边来
他在寻找新的土地
我们族的智者让我学习这种语言
你，你跟他的脸很像
他后来怎么了？
很久之前他被带走了
带去哪里？
跟我来
当你父亲来的时候
我们成为了朋友
后来邪恶的灵们带走了你的父亲
跟许多我们族的一样
恶灵把他们带到巨鸟的巢穴
然后飞过沙漠
恶灵要把他们带到哪里去？
到神居住的天界去
从来没有人回来
（外来语）
我们的智者说
你会带领我们去那里
我？
[SPEAKING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
我们有个传说
有个人能可以给我族人自由
有一天他会出现
那个可以与“利齿”对话的人
最后，勇敢的纳库族人埋葬了逝者
他们告知这片土地上所有的部族
那个可以与“利齿”对话的人出现了
[CHANTING]
他们的号召
是对战争的呼唤
为什么他们认为我可以解救他们？
有些关于你父亲的事情你应该知道
你母亲生你的时候去世了
你父亲不止把你当做他的责任
而是我们整个族
我们当时在挨饿
他不能等到“圣婆”的预言成真
他没有逃跑
他去寻找解救族人的方法
这么长时间你怎么忍心
让我相信我父亲背叛了我们？
因为是他要这样
你父亲拥有“白矛”
他怕他离开以后其他人会跟着他
而遗弃我们的族人
那你现在为什么告诉我？
一个好人
围着自己划一个圈
然后照顾站在圈里的人
他的妻子，他的孩子
另外一些人划个更大的圈
包括进了他们的兄弟姐妹
但是还有一些人
注定要承担伟大的使命
他们必须围着自己划一个
能包括好多好多人的圈
你的父亲就是其中一个这样的人
你要自己决定
是否要成为一样的人
[CHANTING]
他是卡武，我们跑最快的人
（外来语）
他带来了住在那边的部族的口讯
恶灵们掠走了好多人
现在正迅速向巨鸟进发
我们一定要在他们到达巨鸟之前
找到他们
（外来语）
你没有妻子？
你来的前一天
他们杀了她
掠走了我的儿子
（外来语）
[SOBBING]
我是巴库
图杜
不是，我叫巴库
巴库，图杜
（外来语）
[YELLING]
他会杀了他！你得帮他！
放开她!
为了哄你的婊子开心
你居然打我？
尽管试试
你会后悔的
纳库族的消息传的很快
从四面八方来了许多的战士
有移动起来像奔跑中的大鸟的图图族
他们会把眼睛藏在树后
有矮个子的库拉族
像我们的孩子一样高
还有那些头上有血的部落
他们来自没有太阳的山谷
但是他们之中最厉害是候达族
他们的领袖可以代表
这片土地上所有的战士
告诉他如果他的族人跟我们一起
我们会带他们回来的
（外来语）
他说你只是一个小男孩儿
告诉他我的成熟不在外表上
规纳是候达族的，候达人从来不笑
嗯
- 亚哈啦！
他们越走越快
没有因为吃饭或休息慢下来
每天都有更多的战士加入他们
向河流的方向走，快！
“亚哈啦”这个词
是什么意思？
那是你说过的话
“我们会把他们带回来”
（外来语）
巨鸟已经来了
艾弗拉特！
巴库，迪雷来了
[YELLING]
迪雷！
图杜！图杜！
图杜！
图杜，那个拿矛盾的人
他不会放弃的
他跟她
- 呃
- 那男孩也许是对的
迪雷不能像他们一样飞过河流
那谁又能想到他能集结这么多战士呢？
（外来语）
这条河像一条蛇一样穿过沙漠
他说蛇的眼睛一直在太阳的下方
在月亮下它不会移动
有捷径到蛇头么？
我们要越过整个大沙漠
但是没有人可以走那么远
周围的山和沙漠
看起来都是一样的
我们会在里面迷路
我们都会死
我们会找到蛇头的
并且要解救我们的族人
我们得休息
河边的那个人说的是对的
很多天他们一直在原地打转
他们迷了路
然而蛇的眼睛却无处可寻
[GASPING]
你必须忘记
那个跟着你的男人
从来没有人可以穿过沙漠
他们都会死
提提，提提
我找到蛇的眼睛了
你看到那颗星了么？
那一颗？
还记得河边的人是怎么说的么？
它永远在太阳的下方
但是在月亮下，它是不动的
纳库杜，告诉他们我说什么
它会带领我们到达蛇头
当最后的月光照进雅格哈的山谷时
似乎所有的灵都离开了“圣婆”
她已经很多个夜晚都不吃东西
也不说话
因为她知道
她还有最后的使命要完成
智慧的灵
是我，卡坦
[HORN BLOWING]
神所居住的天界
还有蛇头
[GRUNTING]
艾弗拉特，你没事
嘘，不要说话
（外来语）
[BELLOWING]
巴库，这边
人怎么能这样对待“曼纳克”呢？
他们跟我们不同，巴库
那他们是谁？
有人说他们是从星星上来的
还有人相信
当他们的土地沉入海底的时候
他们漂过了圣河
[HORN BLOWING]
他们应该加快速度
我该怎么做，万能的神？
祭献一个人
万能的神不悦
你们必须供奉一个人作为祭祀！
不要！莫哈！
[YELLING]
莫哈！
对我们来说他们人太多了
没有人能把他们带回来
不是，迪雷
那些被强迫工作的人
更多
你认为他们会与我们并肩而战么？
那就要你去探索了
嗯？
（外来语）
啊，迪雷
迪雷
- 图杜
- 别害怕，巴库
我会带你回家的
艾弗拉特在哪里？
女人都睡在另外屋子
但是我今天看到她了
提提跟许多战士一起
在沙漠后等着
他们今天杀了莫哈
他被当成祭品
你们今天到这种地步都是我的错
我希望你原谅
既然“父”选择你领导我们
我们都会跟随你
（外来语）
告诉他们我们有多少战士
让他们跟我们一起作战
他说战士的数量不重要
- 人不能打倒神
- 嘘
他有魔力
他能与“利齿”对话
他说那个盲人知道许多关于神的事情
他曾经是神的仆人但是后来逃跑了
自从那以后他们就把他藏在这里
智者
告诉我们多一些关于神
（外来语）
一开始，他们有三个
不过现在只剩下一个
一定有办法打败他们
他说，一次
只有一次，他听到神说到他的恐惧
他们传说
有个身上有记号的人
能在夜空看到同样图案的记号
他们叫它“巫如・安娜”
“猎者的记号”
天空中最亮的星
他问你是不是有“猎者的记号”
[SHOUTING]
没有那个记号
你不可能打败神
[DOOR OPENS]
等下，等下，你胳膊上的手带
你从哪儿得到的？
那个救了他的命的人给他的
他在哪儿？
他的尸骨跟其他人一样
被埋在了沙漠里
他想知道你为什么问起这个人
他是我的父亲
（外来语）
问他们提提在哪里
[SHOUTS]
他们发现我们了！
[GRUNTING]
我的日子到了
求你，伟大的猎者，不要这样说
我们需要你
他们不会跟我们一直战斗
他们有他们的预言
迪雷
一个预言有很多面
有很多方法可以实现
你的父亲
你的父亲，给了我这个
- 不，伟大的猎者，这个是你的
- 拿去
要像你父亲一样
（外来语）
跟我来
我给你自由
现在你将成为我的人
你偷走一个神的奴隶？
她是我的
这个轮不到你来说！
[CLICKING TONGUE]
（外来语）
万能的神，我不敢
跟您说我们发现了什么
告诉我！
“猎者的…
记号”
[GROWLING]
那不可能！
迪雷
我知道失去好朋友是什么感受
你父亲是我的好朋友
我几乎不记得他了
但是他记得你
每当他提起“圣山”那边的小男孩
他的心会痛
他原本准备回去找你
就在那时他被带走了
迪雷
战士们都在等
我们，作为雅格哈的族人
（外来语）
猎捕最强大的猛兽，“曼纳克”
他是那么强大而我们如此渺小
我们仍然可以打败他
因为我们齐心协力，万众一心
当太阳升起的时候
我们会加入在天界里的兄弟姐妹
然后说服他们跟我一起作战
齐心协力，万众一心！
[YELLING]
怎么回事？
听着，巴库
今天你要成为一名猎者
我？
（外来语）
亚哈啦
[HIGH PRIEST WHIMPERING]
请把这个拿回去吧，万能的神！
安静！叛徒！
伤疤怎么可能是那个记号呢？
你们量了么？
是的，非常仔细
而且很多遍
那个马夫还知道些什么？
有个从山里来的人一直跟着她
还带了很多战士
那么那猎者已经到了！
看，凯伦，看哪
- 那个
- 他？
巴库，我们找到领头牛了
快去！
[SPEAKING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
动手！
规纳，还不行！
好了！
[YELLING]
[GRUNTING]
哈！哈!
- 他们不行的
- “曼纳克”被打了太久了
凯伦，看
[HORN BLOWING]
把所有人都集中到斜坡上！
- 快跑！跑啊！
- 快！快！
凯伦！不要！
[KA'REN YELLING]
[YELLING]
[SCREAMING]
[WHISTLE BLOWS]
[YELLING]
[YELLS]
亚哈啦！
- 亚哈啦！
那些奴隶冲过来了！
她可以阻止他们
把她带出去
拉成两半！
[CHEERING]
亚哈啦！
停！
[SPEAKING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
他说跟随这个女人来的猎者要撤退
否则她就要死
跟这个叛徒一样
撤回你们的山里
你可以带着你的女人一起走
告诉他我接受他的条件
[CROWD MUTTERING]
告诉他我答应
告诉他！
[SPEAKS IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
但我要带走我的族人
每一个雅格哈人
告诉他！
他们是你的了！
问他怎么处置剩下的人
他们属于神，他说
他们将永无休止的工作
不
他们不会
他不是神！
[YELLING]
迪雷！
艾弗拉特！
巴库！
图杜！
不！
不要！
[GASPING]
救命啊！救命！她在流血！
你也得不到她
[CHEERING]
你为我而来
不，不要，求你
求求你
不要
[SOBBING]
他走过如此遥远的旅程
他走到了世界的尽头
他打倒了人们口里那个“万能的神”
归途却不能和艾弗拉特一起
这不是“圣婆”所预言的
但是正当他要永远失去她的时候
却开始了那个蓝眼睛孩子的传说
[TRUMPETING]
[GASPING]
艾弗拉特和迪雷！
[CHEERING]
艾弗拉特带来了我们族人
生命的希望
然而现在，圣婆用她最后的呼吸
将她带了回来
你的父亲希望你把这些东西带回去
这些可以让你们的族人吃饱
告诉他们雅格哈族感谢纳库族
[SPEAKING IN FOREIGN LANGUAGE]
谢谢你，纳库杜兄弟
我的心随你而行，迪雷兄弟
这是他们最后一次见到纳库族的朋友
然后就开始了漫长的归途
他们回来了！他们回来了！
[CHATTERING]
像人们随着“父”而行
看着“父”指引他们的道路
雅格哈族看着艾弗拉特和迪雷
让他们指引族人
当第一轮满月再一次
从雅格哈的山谷升起的时候
她为这片土地带来了第一次丰收
看它们长得多快啊
于是所谓生命的希望
(subtitle from http://shooter.cn by SPlayer1407
终于实现了
(subtitle from http://shooter.cn by SPlayer